Guide to the Thomas Goddard Bergin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Goddard Bergin papers
1930-1974
MS 1629
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.77
(13 boxes, 1 envelope)
The papers contain correspondence; lectures; photographs; writings; and administrative, research and subject files documenting the professional life of Thomas Bergin, eminent scholar of Italian literature and authority on Boccaccio, Dante, and Petrarch. The papers mainly document Bergin's academic career and relate to his involvements with scholars, institutions, and publishers. The papers highlight Bergin's activities to commemorate the 700th anniversary of Dante's birth and his administrative roles at Yale.
Bergin, Thomas Goddard, 1904-1987
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Timothy Dwight College, Yale University, 1992.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Known as "TGB" to most of his students and associates, Thomas Goddard Bergin was an eminent twentieth-century American scholar of Italian literature. He was born in New Haven, Connecticut, on November 17, 1904, the only child of Joseph and Irvinea Jane Frances Goddard Bergin. Joseph Bergin had graduated from Yale University in 1896 and received his M.D. there in 1899. Thomas Bergin went to New Haven High School prior to attending Yale, where he received a B.A. in 1925 and a Ph.D. in romance languages in 1929. Bergin married Florence Bullen of Wailasey (Cheshire, England) on December 30, 1929. They had two children, Winifred and Jennifer.
Bergin began his teaching career at Yale College as an instructor of Italian from 1925 until 1930. He taught at Flora Stone Mather College of Western Reserve University from 1930 to 1935 as an associate professor of Spanish and Italian. Bergin then moved to the New York State Teachers College in Albany, where he served, from 1935 until 1941, as a professor of romance languages. From 1941 to 1948, Bergin was at Cornell University as both professor of romance languages and curator of the Fiske Dante-Petrarch Collections. He also served for a time as chairman of the Division of Literature and acting chairman of the Department of English.
In February 1943, Bergin was appointed head instructor at the United States School of Military Government at Charlottesville, Virginia. Between November 1943 and 1946 Major Bergin was assigned to the headquarters of the Allied Control Commission in Italy, where he served as director of public relations. For his wartime service, Bergin was decorated with the Order of Civil Merit and the Orders of Santi Maurizio e Lazzaro and Corona D'Italia from Italy, and the Order of the British Empire.
Bergin became head of the Spanish and Italian Department at Yale in 1949 and was made the Benjamin Barge Professor of the Romance Languages and Literature in the same year. He was master of Timothy Dwight College from 1953 until 1968, except for the year 1956 when Bergin was a Fulbright Scholar in Italy. He was made the Sterling Professor of Romance Languages and Literature in 1957 and upon retirement in July 1973, became Sterling Professor Emeritus. Memoirs related to his Yale years appear as a chapter entitled "My Native Country" in My Harvard, My Yale (1982), edited by Diana Dubois.
Bergin was an authority on Boccacciot Dantet Petrarch, and the Provenyal troubadours. He also specialized in the study of more modern Italian writers, especially Alberto Moravi, Quasimodo Salvatoret Giovanni Verga, and Giambattista Vico. Besides textbooks and scholarly monographs on French, Italian, Spanish, and Provenyal subjects, including three one-volume Syntheses on Boccacciot Dantet and Petrarch, Bergin published biographies of Italian writers and poets, in English and Italian, and edited The Taming of the Shrew for the Yale Shakespeare series (1954). He also produced translations of several prominent Italian writers and poets, most notably Dante's Divine Comedy, Inferno (1948), Paradise (1954), and Purgatory (1953). Other notable translations include Niccolo Machiavelli's Prince (1947) and Vico's New Science (1948; rev. ed. 1961) with Max Fisch. Bergin compiled, with Ernest H. Wilkins, the indispensable Concordance to the Divine Comedy of Dante Alighieri (1965) for the Dante Society of America. He was also a poet in his own right; some of his poems were collected and edited by A. Bartlett Giamatti and T. K. Swing in Masterpieces From the Files of T.G.B. (1964). Bergin also wrote many articles and book reviews for such publications as Colliers Encyclopedia, The Freeman, the Italian Quarterly, Italica, the New York Times, the Romantic Review, the Virginia Quarterly and the Yale Review. He created the Dante Shelf for Italian Quarterly to review new material on Dante. The bibliography of his works in Italian Literature: Roots and Branches. Essays in Honor of Thomas Goddard Bergin, edited by Giose Rimanelli and Kenneth J. Atchity (1976), includes thirty-seven books, fifteen contributions to books, fifty articles in periodicals, and nearly 500 book reviews.
Bergin played an extremely active part in the 1965 septicentennial celebrations of Dante's birth. He organized a Dante conference at Yale and edited the conference papers, which were published as From Time to Eternity. He also lectured widely during the course of the year long observance.
Bergin was also a Yale historian, author of a history of the residential colleges, and a football enthusiast who vigorously promoted the Yale football team for some twenty years. In "Time and Change," his column for the Yale Alumni Magazine, Bergin addressed many areas of Yale life and history and chronicled the fortunes of the Yale team. He also wrote Gridiron Glory (1978), recounting the fortunes of the Yale football team from 1952 to 1972 and a history of the Harvard Yale football confrontation called The Game: the Harvard-Yale Football Rivalry, 1875-1983 (1984).
Bergin belonged to the American Association of Teachers of Italian (serving as its president in 1947), the Medieval Academy of America, the Dante Society of America, the American Association of University Professors (he was the president of the Yale chapter from 1951 to 1952), and PEN, the international organization of poets, essayists, and novelists. He received honorary degrees from Hofstra College in 1958 and the State University of New York at Binghamton in 1984.
Bergin died on October 30, 1987, at the age of eighty-two, at his home in Madison, Connecticut. Yale honored him posthumously by establishing the Thomas Bergin scholarships for Italian majors in 1989. Timothy Dwight College, furthermore, renamed its dining room in his honor.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence; lectures; photographs; writings; and administrative, research and subject files documenting the professional life of Thomas Bergin, eminent scholar of Italian literature and authority on Boccaccio, Dante, and Petrarch. The papers mainly document Bergin's academic career and relate to his involvements with scholars, institutions, and publishers. The papers highlight Bergin's activities to commemorate the 700th anniversary of Dante's birth and his administrative roles at Yale.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1930-1972. II. Writings, 1937-1974. III. Subject files and photographs, 1952-1971.
Italian language -- Study and teaching; Romance languages -- Study and teaching; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321; Bergin, Thomas Goddard, 1904-1987; Cioffari, Vincenzo, 1905-; DeVito, Anthony J.; Moravia, Alberto, 1907-1990; Musa, Mark, 1934-; Pacifici, Sergio, 1925-; Wilkins, Ernest Hatch, 1880-1966; Dante Society of America; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Italian
- Correspondence, 1930-1972; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of professional correspondence, which documents Bergin's career in academe for the years 1930-1972. The files are arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and may include letters to or from a third party, but all such letters relate in some manner to the primary individual or institution named. Correspondence in other series has been cross-referenced.
  Bergin's correspondence with academic colleagues both at Yale University and elsewhere, and with professional organizations, publishing companies and granting agencies comprises the bulk of the series. The files include correspondence between Bergin and his publishers, Appleton-Century-Crofts and Southern Illinois University Press; fellow Italianists like Sergio Pacifici; and scholarly journals such as Classic Features and La Fiera Letteraria. There are also several folders of Bergin's professional correspondence with well-known scholars of his day, including Mark Musa and Ernest H. Wilkins, as well as with prominent members of the Dante Society of America, such as Anthony J. DeVito.
  This series also documents Bergin's membership in various social clubs and organizations, both in New Haven (the Graduate Club and the Elizabethan Club) and beyond (the Cornell Club, the Andrew Morehouse Trust Association, Inc., and the Savile Club) and underscores Bergin's active membership in international associations. These include PEN and the Institute of Intemational Education, as well as national associations such as the American Council of Learned Societies, the American Association of University Professors and the Author's League of America, Inc. Correspondence relating to Bergin's Fulbright scholarship is documented in folders 4 and 20, and in correspondence with the United States Department of State in folder 84.
  The series includes few strictly personal letters and most of these relate to Bergin's earlier years. Such exchanges are found in the files for Bergin's wife, Florence; sister, E. B. McKenny; and friend, A. B. Canaperia. There is a run of personal letters in "Unidentified," found at the end of the series, written between 1944 and 1945 from an anonymous acquaintance in Cleveland, Ohio.
  - A, 1952-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alberico, Alfred F., 1954-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Commission for Cultural Exchange with Italy, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Andrew Morehouse Trust Association, Inc., 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Appleton-Century-Crofts, 1948-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arnaldo Mondadori Editore [publisher], 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Author's League of America, Inc., 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - B, 1944-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bergin, Florence, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bond, Jerry, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Ca-Cl, 1935-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Co-Cu, 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Canaperia, A. B., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Casa Editrice Valentino Bompiani & C., 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cioffari, Vincenzo, 1951, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    General note
    See also: Series III, box 12, folder 2.
  - Classic Features, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Conference Board of Associated Research Councils. Committee on International Exchange of Persons, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Conti, Bruno, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cornell Club, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cornell University Press, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Costikyan, Clarke, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Crowell-Collier Educational Corporation, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Cunningham, Gilbert F., 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - D, 1944-1971 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Dante Centenary Committee, [1965]
    See: Box 1, folder 18
  - Dante Society of America, 1955-1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - DeVito, Anthony J., 1957-1964 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
    General
    See also:Box 2, folder 26.
  - E, 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Elizabethan Club Board of Governors, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - F, 1951-1963 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - La Fiera Letteraria, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Flores, Angel, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Foster, Kenelm
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 4.
  - Franklin Publications, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Fucilla, J. G., 1952-1960 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - G, 1941-1968 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - George Macy Companies, 1959-1966 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Giamo, Robert, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Gifford, George H., 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Glixon, David M.
    See: Box 3, folder 40.
  - Golino, Carlo, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Graduate Club, 1954..1969 (Box 3, Folder 44-45)
  - Greene, Thomas M.
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 5.
  - Grolier Society, Inc., 1960 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - H, 1944-1968 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - I, 1958-1962 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Institute of International Education, 1950-1958, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Italian Line, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - J, 1945-1959 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Johnston, Waldo C., 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - K, 1950-1968 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Keyser, Jay, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - L, 1951-1968 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Limited Editions Club
    See:Box 3, folder 40.
  - Ma-Mi, 1942-1968 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Mo-Mu, 1944-1970 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Mack, Maynard
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 6.
  - Mario Casalini Ltd., 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - McKenny, E. B. [Bergin's sister], 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Modern Language Association
    See: folder 69
  - Moody, Carol, 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Morghen, Raffaello
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 7.
  - Musa, Mark, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - N, 1953-1960 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - New York Herald Tribune, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - La Nuova Italia Editrice, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - 0, 1946-1954 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Oxford University Press, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - P, 1939-1968 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Pacifici, Sergio, 1953-1963 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Parker, William, 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - PEN, 1961-1968 (Box 4, Folder 70-72)
  - Petrocchi, Giorgio
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 8.
  - Pierson, George
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 9.
  - Proteus Books, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Q, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - R, 1951-1968 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Russell, Peter, 1960-1964 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - S, 1933-1968 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Salvatore, Quasimodo, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Sanesi, Roberto, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Sapegno, Natalino
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 10.
  - Savile Club, 1962-1968 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Scaglione, Aldo
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 11.
  - Shoemaker, William H., 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Southern Illinois University Press, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - T, 1944-1968 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Taylor, Charles H.
    See: Series III, box 12, folder 13.
  - U, 1951-1955, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - V, 1930-1965 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - W, 1952-1967 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Wilkins, Ernest H., 1952-1963 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Y, 1948-1971 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Yale Class of 1925, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Z, 1951-1963 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Unidentified, Circa 1940-1968 (Box 5, Folder 91-92)
- Writings, 1937-1974; Series II
  This series is divided into three sections: lectures and addresses, published writings, and unpublished writings. The bulk of the writings are from the twenty-five years that Bergin spent at Yale as a professor of romance languages, 1948-1973. The series does not document all of Bergin's scholarly writings during this period nor his extensive publications on Yale.
  The lectures and addresses in the first section are arranged alphabetically by the name of the institution at which Bergin spoke. Most date from 1965, when Bergin delivered numerous lectures in many American universities in celebration of the Dante septicentennial. The folders usually contain both correspondence and typescripts of the lecture that Bergin gave at the institution concerned. The text of a lecture may have been delivered at more than one institution.
  The second section, published writings, contains typescripts and handwritten drafts for several of Bergin's major books, including the Concordance to the Divine Comedy of Dante Alighieri with Ernest Wilkins (1965), Bergin's handbook on Dante (1965), A Diversity of Dante (1969), and Bergin's translations of major works by Dante and Petrarch (induding the letters, Bucolicum Carmen, in Latin). There is also much correspondence between Bergin and publishers and scholars with whom he collaborated in his writing projects. This section also includes book reviews that Bergin wrote for scholarly and literary journals and three folders of original poems. Bergin's many poems in the New Haven daily newspapers were signed under the pseudonym "Tom Goddard" or the anagram "Homer N. Bigstag." The files in this section are arranged in alphabetical order by title.
  The final section, unpublished writings, is small. It includes a rejected article from the Virginia Quarterly Review, an unidentified, annotated manuscript on Sir Thomas More, and miscellaneous verse.
  - Lectures and addresses
    - Albertus Magnus College, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - American International College, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Catholic University of Arnerica, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Danbury State College, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Dante Society, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Georgetown University, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Hofstra College, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Indiana University
      - 1957 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - 1967 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Nasson College, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - New Haven Free Public Library, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Pennsylvania State University, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Rhode Island College, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Rutgers State University, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - San Diego State College, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - State University of New York at Buffalo, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Trinity College, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - University of Cincinnati, Undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - University of Connecticut, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - University of Kansas, Circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 21)
      On common themes in the literature of the romance languages.
    - University of Massachusetts, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - University of Puerto Rico, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - University of Texas, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - University of Toronto, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - University of Virginia, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Yale University
      - Alumni seminar, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - Calhoun College, Undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
        On education and language.
      - Division of the Humanities ["Postwar Italian Writers"], 1952 (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Freshman speech, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Graduate Club, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Graduate Club, Undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
        On symbolism of monsters and the wood in Dante and Vico.
      - Graduation speech, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 33)
      - Parents' Day address, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 34)
      - Romance Club, Undated (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Published writings
    - Book reviews, Circa 1951-1966 (Box 7, Folder 36-37)
    - Bucolicum Carmen, II-V, VIII [drafts and correspondence], Circa 1971-1974 (Box 7, Folder 38-42)
    - C. W. Post College project, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - "The Comedy -- Letter and Spirit" [ Virginia Quarterly Review ], 1965 (Box 8, Folder 44)
      See also: Box 6, folder 6 and folder 18.
    - Concordance to the Divine Comedy of Dante Alighieri, 1959-1964
      See also: Series I, box 5, folder 87.
      - Contract and correspondence (Box 8, Folder 45)
      - Corrections and preface (Box 8, Folder 46)
      - Instructions (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Current History [article for], 1955 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Dante, 1965
      - Drafts
        - "Allegory" (Box 8, Folder 49)
        - "The Convivio " (Box 8, Folder 50)
        - "Dante's City" (Box 8, Folder 51)
        - "Dante's Europe" (Box 8, Folder 52)
        - "Dante's Life" (Box 8, Folder 53)
        - "Doctrine" (Box 8, Folder 54)
        - "Lesser Works" (Box 8, Folder 55)
        - " De Monarchia " (Box 8, Folder 56)
        - "Narrative -- Paradiso " (Box 8, Folder 57)
        - "Narrative and Pattern -- the Inferno " (Box 8, Folder 58)
        - "Notes and Bibliography" (Box 9, Folder 59)
        - " Purgatory -- Narrative" (Box 9, Folder 60)
        - "Reading and Study" (Box 9, Folder 61)
        - "Rhymes" (Box 9, Folder 62)
        - "Tools and Techniques" (Box 9, Folder 63)
        - "The Vita Nuova " (Box 9, Folder 64)
        - " De Vulgari Eloquentia " (Box 9, Folder 65)
      - Reviews (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - "Dante Alighieri" [ Encyclopedia of Philosophy article], 1967 (Box 9, Folder 67)
    - A Diversity of Dante, Circa 1969
      - "Dante's Comedy -- Letter and Spirit" [chapter 2]
        See: Box 6, folder 6 and folder 18.
      - "Light from Mars" [chapter 8]
        See: Box 6, folder 3.
      - " Paradise IX " [chapter 7] (Box 9, Folder 68-70)
      - "The Women of the Comedy " [chapter 5] (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - Inferno, Undated
      - Footnotes (Box 9, Folder 72)
      - Revisions (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - Italian Sampler [book reviews of], 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Italy: from Chaucer to Sinclair Lewis, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Master Pieces, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Moravia, Alberto [biographical sketch], Circa 1953 (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Paradiso, Circa 1954 (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - Poems, 1938-circa 1965 (Box 10, Folder 79-81)
    - The Pressure is Mine, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Purgatory, Circa 1953 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Rhymes of Petrarch, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 84-85)
    - "Trails through Vico's Forest", Undated (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Villaroel, Giuseppe [translations of poetry], Circa 1958 (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - La Vita d'Ogg i, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - "Whose Dante; Which Comedy ?" [from Perspectives on the Divine Comedy ], Circa 1967 (Box 10, Folder 89-90)
  - Unpublished writings
    - "Seven Hills of Snow", 1957 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Poetry, 1956, undated (Box 11, Folder 92-93)
    - Unidentified, Undated (Box 11, Folder 94-96)
- Subject Files and Photographs, 1952-1971; Series III
  This series is arranged in five sections. They are: Dante septicentennial, Italian literature, Yale University, Personal, and Photographs.